Finding Aid for Carlton F. Wells papers, 1910-1994
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Carlton F. Wells papers 1910-1994
Wells, Carlton F. (Carlton Frank), 1898-
19 linear feet
86441 Aa 2
Professor of English at University of Michigan. Correspondence, diaries, and topical files relating to his interest in English grammar and usage, his evaluation of various dictionaries, his interest in Polish-American relations, and the controversy surrounding Henshaw Ward's denial of Peary's discovery of the North Pole.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Carlton F. Wells (donor no. 2708 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Carlton Frank Wells was born April 30, 1898 in Vicksburg, MI, the son of Frank W. and Anna H. Wells. After graduation from Western State Normal High School in Kalamazoo, he entered the University of Michigan from which he received his bachelor's degree in 1920 and his master's degree in 1922. Wells joined the faculty at the University of Michigan in 1921 as an instructor in English. He would teach in the English Department until his retirement in 1968. During his career, Wells served as chairman of Freshman English in the Literary College from 1935 to 1949. He was also faculty advisor to foreign students from 1922 to 1929. Toward the close of World War II and immediately thereafter, he served as chairman of the Michigan Committee of Americans for Poland.
Professor Wells was a member of Phi Beta Kappa, the National Council of Teachers of English and the Michigan Council of Teachers of English. He was co-editor of several texts for freshman English and in 1962, he published, with a colleague The Recognition of Emily Dickinson. For 10 years following his retirement, he served as secretary-treasurer of the U of M Chapter of Phi Beta Kappa. Wells died December 4, 1994.
The Wells collection is comprised of the following series: Subject file; Personal diaries; Robert E. Peary; and Other papers.
Subjects:
Cosmopolitan Club (University of Michigan); English language--Dictionaries.; Michigan Committee of Americans for Poland.; North Pole.; Peary, Robert E. (Robert Edwin), 1856-1920.; Phelps, William Lyon, 1865-1943.; Poland.; Polish Americans--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of English Language and Literature.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945.; Wells, Carlton F. (Carlton Frank), 1898-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Cosmopolitan Club (University of Michigan); Quadrangle Club (University of Michigan); United States. Army. Students' Army Training Corps (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Students.; University of Michigan. Men's Glee Club.; University of Michigan. Spring Games--1924.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1911-1920.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1921-1930.; Wells, Carlton F. (Carlton Frank), 1898-; Wells family.; Students, Foreign--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946.; Coughlin, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1891-1979.; Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1881-1959.; Guest, Edgar A. (Edgar Albert), 1912-; Hornberger, Theodore, 1906-1975.; Smith, Gerald L. K. (Gerald Lyman Kenneth), 1898-1976; Ward, Henshaw, 1872-1935.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Subject file
  The Subject file, arranged alphabetically, includes correspondence with Wells' many friends and colleagues as well as other files detailing his scholarly interests and organizational activities. There are, for instance, extensive files relating to his analysis of new editions of dictionaries, particularly Webster's New World Dictionary 1953 edition, to his participation with the Michigan Committee of Americans for Poland, and to his interest the usage of the English language.
  - Baker, Ray Stannard 1929-1941 (Box 1)
  - China 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Communism 1951 (Box 1)
  - Crocker, Lionel
    - 1918-1919, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1921-1922, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Dictionaries
    - American College Dictionary ( 1947 ) vs. Webster's New World Dictionary ( 1953 )
      - Notes comparing, 2 folders (Box 1)
      - Correspondence
        - January-February 1953 (Box 1)
        - March 1953 (Box 1)
        - April 1953 (Box 1)
        - May-December 1953 (Box 1)
        - 1954 (Box 1)
      - Printed material (Box 1)
    - Random House 1966 (Box 1)
  - Ellis, William, re. publication of his manuscript Pick-Up 1937-1938, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - English no. 92 Lectures (Box 1)
  - Essays for Our Times circa 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Guest, Edgar and Edgar Jr. 1927-1967 (Box 1)
  - Hornberger, Theodore
    - 1932-1939, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1940-1949, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - 1950-1959 (Box 1)
    - 1960-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1970-1974, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - correspondence with Rudolph Willard (Box 1)
  - Literary Map of Michigan 1963-1965
    - Correspondence with Esther Loughlin 1964-1965 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Robert Granville 1963 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Committee reports and compiled biographical material, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - MacArthur (removal of General Douglas MacArthur) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence
    - Undated (Box 2)
    - 1892-1919 (Box 2)
    - 1920-1929, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 1930-1939, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 1940-1949, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - 1950-1959, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - 1960-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970-1979 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Michigan Committee of Americans for Poland 1943-1960
    - American Legion Magazine (Box 2)
    - American Mercury (Box 2)
    - Detroit News (Box 2)
    - Life Magazine (Box 2)
    - Thaddeus Machrowicz (Box 2)
    - Polish Press Agency, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Time Magazine (Box 2)
    - W.L. White (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1943-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1945 (Box 2)
      - 1946, 5 folders (Box 2)
      - 1947, 3 folders (Box 2)
      - 1948-1960 (Box 2)
    - Financial (Box 2)
    - Printed, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Osborn, Chase, re. his book about Henry Schoolcraft and Hiawatha legend 1958 (Box 3)
  - Phelps, William Lyon 1929-1932 (Box 3)
  - Richmond, Rouldus 1936-1937 (Box 3)
  - School correspondence of Carlton Wells 1911-1919, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Technical file on English Usage
    - Ain't (Box 3)
    - Alexander, Jack re. lexicography 1946-1949 (Box 3)
    - All right (Box 3)
    - Bad (Box 3)
    - Churchill, Winston 1951 (Box 3)
    - Data v. datum (Box 3)
    - Feminine Designations (Box 3)
    - Fewer, less (Box 3)
    - Fragments (Box 3)
    - Got, gotten (Box 3)
    - Healthy, healthful (Box 3)
    - Regimen, regime, régime (Box 3)
    - Split Infinitive (Box 3)
    - Spoken Word (Box 3)
    - Style (Box 3)
  - Trip to Turkey by Helen Wells 1927-1928, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Trip to United Kingdom 1924 (Box 3)
  - World War II
    - Re. war with Germany 1940-1941 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with and about Gerald L.K.-Smith and Father Charles Coughlin (Box 3)
    - Correspondence re. posters and films 1942-1951, 3 folders (Box 3)
- Personal Diaries
  The Personal diaries series begins in 1911 and runs almost continuously until his death in 1994. There are but a few early gaps in coverage, 1912 to 1917. Beyond that, the scores of volumes show Wells to be a conscientious observer of current and local events. This series also includes a few volumes of his wife, Cecilia D. Wells' diaries.
  - 1911 (Box 3)
  - 1918 (Box 3)
  - 1919 (Box 3)
  - January 1920-July 1921 (Box 3)
  - July 1921-December 1924 (Box 3)
  - October 1924-August 1926 (Box 3)
  - September 1926-December 1928 (Box 3)
  - September 1929-February 1931 (of Cecilia D. Wells) (Box 3)
  - United Kingdom Trip 1924 (Box 3)
  - January 1928-January 1929 (Box 4)
  - August-September 1928 (trip to Europe) (Box 4)
  - January 1929-May 1930 (Box 4)
  - June 1930-April 1932 (Box 4)
  - April 1932-November 1932 (Box 4)
  - November 1932-February 1933 (Box 4)
  - February 1933-June 1933 (Box 4)
  - June 1933-May 1934 (Box 4)
  - May 1934-September 1935 (Box 5)
  - January-August 1936 (Box 5)
  - August 1936-May 1937 (Box 5)
  - May 1938-August 1938 (Box 5)
  - August 1938-April 1939 (Box 5)
  - May 1939-June 1940 (Box 5)
  - June 1940-May 1942 (Box 5)
  - May 1942-July 1943 (Box 5)
  - July 1943-September 1944 (Box 5)
  - October 1944-September 1945 (Box 6)
  - September 1945-December 1946 (Box 6)
  - January 1947-June 1948 (Box 6)
  - June 1948-September 1949 (Box 6)
  - June 1948-September 1949 (Box 6)
  - September 1949-October 1950 (Box 6)
  - November 1950-August 1951 (Box 6)
  - August 1951-December 1951 (Box 6)
  - January-June 1952 (Box 6)
  - July 1952-March 1953 (Box 6)
  - April 1953-March 1954 (Box 7)
  - March 1954-February 1955 (Box 7)
  - February 1955-November 1955 (Box 7)
  - November 1955-June 1956 (Box 7)
  - June-December 1956 (Box 7)
  - December 1956-September 1957 (Box 7)
  - September 1957-July 1958 (Box 7)
  - July 1958-April 1959 (Box 7)
  - May-November 1959 (Box 8)
  - December 1959-September 1960 (Box 8)
  - October 1960-April 1961 (Box 8)
  - April 1961-April 1962 (Box 8)
  - April 1962-February 1963 (Box 8)
  - February 1963-July 1963 (Box 8)
  - July 1963-March 1964 (Box 8)
  - April 1964-November 1964 (Box 8)
  - December 1964-April 1965 (Box 9)
  - April 1965-January 1966 (Box 9)
  - January-May 1966 (Box 9)
  - May 1966-April 1967 (Box 9)
  - May-December 1967 (Box 9)
  - December 1967-April 1968 (Box 9)
  - May-December 1968 (Box 9)
  - December 1968-July 1969 (Box 9)
  - August 1969-March 1970 (Box 9)
  - March-December 1970 (Box 9)
  - January-September 1971 (Box 10)
  - September 1971-April 1972 (Box 10)
  - April-September 1972 (Box 10)
  - October 1972-April 1973 (Box 10)
  - April-November 1973 (Box 10)
  - November 1973-May 1974 (Box 10)
  - May-August 1974 (Box 10)
  - August 1974-March 1975 (Box 10)
  - March-August 1975 (Box 10)
  - August-December 1975 (Box 10)
  - January-June 1976 (Box 11)
  - June-October 1976 (Box 11)
  - October 1976-February 1977 (Box 11)
  - March-June 1977 (Box 11)
  - July-December 1977 (Box 11)
  - December 1977-March 1978 (Box 11)
  - March-June 1978 (Box 11)
  - July 1978-March 1979 (Box 11)
  - March-July 1979 (Box 11)
  - July-December 1979 (Box 12)
  - December 1979-May 1980 (Box 12)
  - June-November 5, 1980 (Box 12)
  - November 1980-April 1981 (Box 12)
  - April-September 1981 (Box 12)
  - September 1981-January 1982 (Box 12)
  - February 1-June 18, 1982 (Box 12)
  - June-September 1982 (Box 12)
  - September 14, 1982-August 18, 1985 (Box 13)
  - August 19, 1985-November 1990 (Box 15)
  - 1927-1929, 1954-1955 (of Cecelia D. Wells) (Box 15)
  - November 1990-1994 (Box 19)
- Robert E. Peary
  The Robert E. Peary series which came to the library subsequent to the Subject file series concerns the controversy surrounding Henshaw Ward's denial that Peary was the discoverer of the North Pole. The topic was one that intrigued Wells over many years but especially in his retirement. Included is both collected materials and correspondence with individuals knowledgeable about the topic.
  - Cook, Alan 1974 (Box 14)
  - Crombie, Robert 1973 (Box 14)
  - Euller, John (articles) (Box 14)
  - Forbes, Lachlan M. 1970-1973 (Box 14)
  - Gould, Laurence 1970 (Box 14)
  - Hayes, J. Gordon (articles) (Box 14)
  - Kish, George 1970 (Box 14)
  - Lord, Walter 1970 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Mohler, Orren 1973-1974 (Box 14)
  - National Geographic Magazine
    - Article 1954 (Box 14)
    - Correspondence 1973 (Box 14)
  - Rawlins, Dennis 1931-1976 (Box 14)
  - Reddig, James C. 1973 (Box 14)
  - Reviews 1930-1973 (Box 14)
  - Vetter, Helene Cook 1973 (Box 14)
  - Ward, Henshaw
    - Correspondence 1934-1936 (Box 14)
    - Manuscript copy of "The Peary Myth: A Study in American Glory" (Box 14)
  - Wood, Florence Ward 1937-1983 (Box 14)
  - Wright, Theon 1970 (Box 14)
  - Master Contents list of Peary Series (Box 14)
- Other papers
  The Other papers series includes correspondence from Wells' later career and retirement. There are also photographs and a scrapbook of trips taken by the University of Michigan's Cosmopolitan Club, 1922-1928.
  - 1987 accession: Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Photographs
    - Family and friends (Box 14)
    - Friends, Academic (Box 14)
    - Groups (Box 14)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
    - Self (Box 14)
  - Scrapbook re trips taken by U-M's Cosmopolitan Club, 1922-1928 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence (arranged alphabetically)
    - A-M (Box 16)
    - M-W (Box 17)
    - W-Z (Box 18)
  - Vanity correspondence (Box 18)
  - School papers (Box 18)
  - Miscellanea (Box 18)